<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sidequests</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sidequests</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 22:41:07 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building Piskvor Prime: A Five-in-a-Row Game with Personality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/piskvor-prime/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 22:41:07 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/piskvor-prime/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Minimax to Monte Carlo Tree Search: Progress Update</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/mcts-progress-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/mcts-progress-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-minimax-to-mcts&#34;&gt;From Minimax to MCTS&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the past few days, I&amp;rsquo;ve made some big strides in improving the AI for my game. What started as a basic &lt;strong&gt;minimax + heuristic&lt;/strong&gt; approach quickly ran into limitations. The game is timing-sensitive and rewards long-term planning — not something minimax handles easily with shallow depth and static evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, I switched gears and started working on a &lt;strong&gt;Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS)&lt;/strong&gt; implementation — and I’m really happy with the progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Minimax to Monte Carlo Tree Search: Smarter AI for Mars Colony</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/from-minimax-to-mcts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/from-minimax-to-mcts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on the AI for my game, which takes place on a toroidal grid with dynamic systems like population growth, energy networks, and resource management. It’s a complex environment with a lot of long-term planning involved — and that makes writing a good AI surprisingly tricky.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Up until now, I’ve been using a classic &lt;strong&gt;minimax&lt;/strong&gt; algorithm with a &lt;strong&gt;handcrafted evaluation function&lt;/strong&gt;. Here&amp;rsquo;s the setup:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A minimax tree search (depth-limited)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A fixed &lt;code&gt;evaluate()&lt;/code&gt; function that tries to guess how &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; a state is, based on:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Population size&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Energy yield&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Proximity to resources&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Habitat count&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Loops in pipe networks (bad!)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And more&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While this approach works &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt; in simple cases, it really struggles in the kinds of situations my game cares most about — especially when &lt;strong&gt;timing and sequence of actions&lt;/strong&gt; matter more than just static advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Loops on Torus</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/finding-loops/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2025 12:04:56 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/finding-loops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-problem-statement&#34;&gt;🧩 Problem Statement&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my current game project, I&amp;rsquo;m working with a toroidal 2D grid (a grid that wraps around like a donut). On this grid, certain tiles are marked as “paths.” These paths can form closed loops, and I wanted a way to &lt;strong&gt;detect and count the number of such loops&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There’s a twist:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The grid &lt;strong&gt;wraps around both horizontally and vertically&lt;/strong&gt; (like Pac-Man).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I only get the path data as a &lt;strong&gt;list of coordinates&lt;/strong&gt;, not a full 2D array.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And there may be &lt;strong&gt;multiple disconnected path components&lt;/strong&gt; on the grid.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;-strategy&#34;&gt;🧠 Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to trace every possible loop (which is hard and inefficient), I used a classic trick from graph theory:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing a turn-based strategy game bot</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/writing-a-turn-based-game-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 19:10:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/writing-a-turn-based-game-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why am I writing a bot for a turn-based game in 2025?&#xA;We are currently developing a turn based strategy &lt;a href=&#34;https://martians-nine.vercel.app&#34;&gt;game&lt;/a&gt; with Michal Srb. The multiplayer is done, what remains is the AI. This series of blogposts will follow my journey towards implementing a (hopefully) decent oponnent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From what I know now, it seems to be the best to:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Implement a basic minimax strategy on a simpler game.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Implement interesting heuristics on that simpler game.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use Monte-Carlo tree search on that simpler game.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Port one of those strategies to our game.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Keep an eye our on the LLMs in the process. I will implement both a strategist that uses LLM queries and use LLMs to help me with the code.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;minimax&#34;&gt;Minimax&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The simplest game I could think of is Tic Tac Toe and it&amp;rsquo;s bigger brother called &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi%C5%A1kvorky&#34;&gt;Piskvorky&lt;/a&gt; (Czech only) or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gomoku&#34;&gt;Gomoku&lt;/a&gt;. A simple warmup is a Tic Tac Toe on 3x3 board.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating Graphics for a Turn-Based Game</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/generating_interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 21:03:29 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/vojtanyc/posts/generating_interfaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are currently developing a turn-based strategy &lt;a href=&#34;https://martians-nine.vercel.app&#34;&gt;game&lt;/a&gt; we tentativelly call Mars Colony with a friend. Here are the rules:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let me explain you the rules first:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The game is a turn-based strategy where two players play against each other. Each player tries to connect energy resources (green circles with R) to habitats (circles labeled with P) using pipes (the thick lines).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each habitat has a certain population (the number that appears after P). The goal of the game is to get a total population of 30 before your oponent and not run out of energy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
